Mss.B.R91,.d,.m,.n
American Philosophical Society
Richard Joel Russell papers, [ca. 1930s-1971]
Circa 1930-1971
Mss.B.R91,.d,.m,.n
American Philosophical Society
6.0 Linear feet
This collection includes correspondence, lectures, notebooks, reports, photographs, and maps. There is much in Russell's papers concerning the Department of Geography at L.S.U., as well as faculty and research concerns and other needs of the university.
Ca. 5000 items, 6000 linear feet.
Russell, Richard Joel, 1895-1971
Box 1-12
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Richard Joel and accessioned, 1967 (1967 2626ms). See in-house shelf list for additional accession numbers and dates.
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: 180 black and white photographs, maps, diagrams, and sketches of pre-historic Archaic, Tchefuncte, Troysville-Coles, Taensa, Plaquemine, and Caddo Indian sites in parishes throughout Louisiana taken from 1934-1950. Images accompany reports by Russell, with contributions from fellow Louisiana State University colleagues Henry V. Howe and Fred Kniffen, of field investigations of shorelines in legal dispute by various corporations. Site locations include: Chicot Pass, Bayous Perot, Sale, Freshwater, and Choctaw, Grand Lake, and Red River. Geographical and geological in nature, the photographs include shell middens, pottery shards, and mounds of early Native American settlements.
Maps note: There are approximately 150 maps in this collection. They are in various notebooks which give a general indication of the area and sometimes a date. The maps generally are quite small and were sketched on the site of the topographical or geological study then underway. (Realms of Gold, 40).
Biographical/Historical note
Richard Joel Russell was a geologist and geographer. He studied the river deltas of America (chiefly the Mississippi River), Spain, France, and Turkey. He also studied the coastal morphology of the Gulf of Mexico; stream patterns; arid areas of the United States; and he worked on a climatic map of California. He came to Louisiana State University in 1928, where he created the Department of Geography, and he remained there all his academic life.
Howe, Henry V. (Henry Van Wagenen), 1896-; Jones, Wellington Downing, 1886-; Kniffen, Fred Bowerman, 1900-; Lawson, Andrew C., (Andrew Cowper), 1861-1952; Louderback, George D., (George Davis), 1874-1957; Louisiana State University and Agricultural and Mechanical College. -- Dept. of Geography.; Mencken, H. L., (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Morgan, James P., (James Plummer), 1919-; Penck, Albrecht; Price, W. Armstrong, (William Armstrong), 1889-; Roy, Chalmer John, 1907-; Sauer, Carl Ortwin, 1889-1975; Sternberg, Hilgard O'Reilly; Thornthwaite, C. W., (Charles Warren), 1899-1963; United States. -- Office of Naval Research.; Caddo Indians; Diagrams.; Diaries.; Gelatin silver prints; Geography.; Geology.; Indians of North America--Louisiana--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Louisiana--Caddo Parish--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Louisiana--Cameron Parish--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Louisiana--Iberia Parish--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Louisiana--Lafourche Parish--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Louisiana--LaSalle Parish--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Louisiana--Saint Mary Parish--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Louisiana--Tensas Parish--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Louisiana--Vermilion Parish--Antiquities; Lectures.; Louisiana -- Description and travel.; Maps.; Morocco -- Description and travel.; Naval research -- United States.; Notebooks.; Physical geography -- Rhône River Valley (Switzerland and France); Prehistoric peoples--Louisiana; Public lands -- Louisiana.; Rhône River Delta (France); Sketches.; Southeast Indians; Taensa Indians; Turkey -- Description and travel.
- Report: Age of Island in Chicot, Louisana, 26 Jan. 1942
- Report: Bayou Ledet, Dec. 1939
- Report: Bayou L'Ours, LaFourche Parish, Louisiana (Indian Mounds), Oct. 1940
- Report: Bayou Perot Region, LaFourche Parish, Louisiana #1, 1944
- Report: Bayou Perot Region, LaFourche Parish, Louisiana #2, 1944
  - Tchefuncte shell mound, 1944
- Report: Bayou Sale [St. Mary Parish, Louisiana] #1, 1941-1942
- Report: Bayou Sale [St. Mary Parish, Louisiana] #2, 1941-1942
  - Troysville-Coles Creek site, 1942
- Report: Bayou Sale [St. Mary Parish, Louisiana] #3, 1941-1942
- Report: Bayou Sale [St. Mary Parish, Louisiana] #4, 1941-1942
- Report: Bayou Sale [St. Mary Parish, Louisiana] #5, 1941-1942
- Report: Bayou Sale [St. Mary Parish, Louisiana] #6, 1941-1942
- Report: Catahoula Lake-elevation of the shore line. LaSalle Parish, Louisiana #1, 1941
- Report: Catahoula Lake-elevation of the shore line. LaSalle Parish, Louisiana #2, 1942
- Report: Choctaw Bayous, Tensas Parish, Louisiana #1, 1943-1944
- Report: Choctaw Bayous, Tensas Parish, Louisiana #2, 1943-1944
- Report: Choctaw Bayous, Tensas Parish, Louisiana #3, 1943-1944
- Report: Choctaw Bayous, Tensas Parish, Louisiana #4, 1943-1944
- Report: Determination of the Mean, High-Water, Lake St. John, Concordia Parish, Louisiana, 1944
- Report: Freshwater Bayou Canal, Louisiana #1, 1950
- Report: Freshwater Bayou Canal, Louisiana #2, 1950
  - Plaquemine pottery shards, 1950
  - Plaquemine pottery shards, 1950
- Report: Geological Conditions along Texas and Pacific Railroad, between Gretna and Shreveport, Louisiana #1, 1941
- Report: Geological Conditions along Texas and Pacific Railroad, between Gretna and Shreveport, Louisiana #2, 1941
- Report: Grand Lake, Parish of Cameron, Louisiana #1, 1934
- Report: Grand Lake, Parish of Cameron, Louisiana #2, 1934
- Report: Lake Hatch Region, Terrebonne Parish, Louisiana, 1939
- Report: Long Lake, LaFourche Parish, Louisiana #1, 1940
- Report: Long Lake, LaFourche Parish, Louisiana #2, 1940
- Report: Paradis Area, St. Charles Parish, Louisiana #1, 1940
- Report: Paradis Area, St. Charles Parish, Louisiana #2, 1940
- Report: Sunflower Plantation Study, Red River, Louisiana #1, 1944
- Report: Sunflower Plantation Study, Red River, Louisiana #2, 1944